[Music]
so just I just want to express my
gratitude to everyone who's come today
thank you for coming so my name is
Maxwell ramstad I am a postdoctoral
fellow here at the Jewish general I work
with Lawrence and I work mainly on this
approach called active inference that
I'll be presenting today so my talk
appropriately is called a tutorial on
active inference from the predictive
brain to socio-cultural regimes of
expectation and the talk basically is
going to come in for part four parts
yeah so the the first is basically a
motivation of the problems that that
we're trying to address using active
inference so I'll present on the one
hand the problems per se that active
inference addresses like the the space
of problems in which active inference
lives and then I'll move on to a few
more specific motivations about why an
approach like this might be interesting
then I'll turn to its what's known in
the literature as predictive processing
which is basically this active inference
scheme applied to the brain then I'll
I'll move to active inference per se
these two sections will kind of come
together I mean the the predictive
processing part is just the application
of this framework to the brain so
they're not all that distinct although
you know if you get into the more
technical debates there there are some
distinctions that we can return to that
and finally if time allows all I'll
discuss some of the multi scale
extensions of active inference so going
beyond models of brains and cells to
like this kind of integrated view of
systems of systems of systems that are
nested the ones within the others and
the kind of
together thanks to this act of inference
framework so first I guess a discussion
of the motivation and problems so
basically the problem I think that
active inference helps us solve most
clearly is a problem of multi scale
systems so this is a picture of McGill
University in slightly warmer times so
McGill University is a is a complex
system it's a system that's composed of
several different parts right some of
which are living some of which are not
right so the the faculty the student
body the support staff right but also
all those are living and and some some
things that arguably are not right like
the the building's right the rest of the
physical infrastructure labs and so
forth well if you zero in on one one
component of this the living ones right
so say the student body in McGill is
itself composed of bodies right and
bodies as we know are composed of cells
and cells make up organ networks right
that eventually make up organisms
organisms themselves interact in social
groups and eventually make up social
networks one of which may be the most
evil I've posted the image of right here
so systems within systems within systems
right we are systems within systems
within systems that's kind of the
takeaway of this slide so if you look at
the structure of the brain the brain
structure in a sense recapitulates the
structure of the environment in which
it's encapsulated so if you look at the
brain structure the structure of the
brain this is from a paper by a park and
frisson what you'll notice is basically
a repeated encapsulation of networks
within networks within networks right so
you know dendritic formation at one
level you know and if you zoom out a bit
you have networks of neurons and then if
you zoom out even more you have brain
regions interacting with brain regions
and so forth and what we what we notice
is that there's a there's a a
segregation in
a kind of spatial temporal segregation
of the interactions between brain
regions that in a sense corresponds to
and captures the regularities of the
kind of statistical segregation that we
see out in the out in the world around
us right things change in relevant ways
at different scales at different spatial
and temporal scales so this is something
that we'll return to and so you know up
until very recently this was lacking in
a literature but suppose we wanted to
study all these levels you know together
in an integrated fashion you know
recognizing the interest and dignity of
all these levels right so suppose we
wanted to construct a framework that was
able to address you know I've plotted
here this is from a paper that I wrote
with Carl for soon and Paul Badcock a
while back I've plotted spacial
dimensions on the y-axis and temporal
dimensions on the x axis so we would
like is a theory that can in an
integrated fashion offer an explanation
for the way that systems behave from the
subcellular level through to the
cellular level the the level of tissues
organs and organ networks to organisms
all the way eventually to speciation the
construction of specifically design
Mischa's and from from it this is from
the spatial point of view but from the
temporal point of view we would also
like an account that's able to account
for the the variety of temporal scales
that are involved in the phenomena of
interest right so from mechanistic
processes occurring over milliseconds
all the way to you know phylogeny and
adaptive radiation which span you know
hundreds of thousands if not millions of
years so so that's one that's the
motivation of the problem how would we
how would we address all these different
spatial and temporal scales in a
principled way what kind of framework
would be able to enable that okay so
that's the problem one motivation for
thinking about active inferences
particular in particular is a it's an
observation it's that most
self-organizing systems in nature tend
to dissipate
right so from galaxies and stars to
lightning bolts and tornadoes almost all
really like all and I mean that in a
very strong sense almost all systems
that self organize in nature self
organized to equilibrium so does this
mean if we had to unpack it in a kind of
basic way well first first we should
note that these self-organizing systems
can consume the gradients around which
they organize right so if for instance
you think of a lightning bolt lightning
bolt self-organizes around a charge
gradient right and in striking the
lightning bolt consumes the gradient
around which it's self-organized
effectively leaving the entire system at
equilibrium so the same could be said
for tornadoes although although now it's
not a charge gradient it's a temperature
gradient and a weather system but the
the main takeaway is that for almost all
systems in nature self-organization
serves to increase entropy so in this
context entropy is a measure of spread
you can think about it roughly as a
quantification of how many different
configurations the system could be in
right so if you think of a gas versus
say a crystal or water or a solid in a
gas the Constituent particles could be
in any number of different
configurations right like this this one
that I'm pointing to at the end of my
finger this little molecule of gas might
be at the other end of the room in like
you know 20 minutes there there's
there's less constraint as to where the
the the little particle will end up or
is if you think of a crystal well the
the kind of regular leti structure and a
crystal means that there are only ever
local interactions and that you can
predict with a high degree of
reliability what any different when any
any given particle what state it will be
in right so high entropy means a high
number of available configurations low
low entropy means a low number of
available configurations so so back to
this most systems in nature right
self-organized to equilibrium they they
dissipate they increase and
but other systems a self-organized and
do not write bunny rabbits and tigers
and you know I don't want to make
assumptions about you but I assume you
as well don't self organize to
equilibrium right you we self organize
to the this regime of states that's in
effect very far from equilibrium right i
I don't exist at room temperature my
core body temperature is about
thirty-six and a half degrees Celsius I
imagine yours is roughly the same you
know so we we we manage to stay far away
from equilibrium and the question is
well how how do we manage to do this so
here is gonna be my first kind of
technical excursus I'm gonna present to
you a the state space formalism from
dynamical systems and this will help us
think a bit more formally about what I
just said so a state space description
is something borrowed from dynamical
Systems Theory and the idea is to
construct an abstract space that
represents all possible states of a
system right so it's it's literally that
we're just constructing a state space
right so like a a mathematical object
with dimensions that you can kind of
move around in right and this space is
going to represent all the possible
states that our system can be in and so
how do we do this well basically for
every way that the system can change
right aka for every variable in the
system what we're gonna do is plot one
dimension in this space so we're gonna
say okay this this variable corresponds
to a dimension in this space that we're
constructing so suppose you have a very
simple physical system with a
temperature and a size right then you
might represent it this way right one of
the dimensions corresponds to
temperature the other dimension
corresponds to size and so what you'll
notice already from this set up is that
a point in this space here is already a
complete description of the system that
we're interested in right just so to
recap the argument every dimension in
this space corresponds to a variable in
the system therefore every point in the
system corresponds to assigning a value
to every
variable so essentially a position along
the dimension right and so that might
seem like a banal observation but it
allows us to to say interesting things
about which you might call the intrinsic
geometry of a system in terms of its
phase space so for example you might
want to say well in in the whole space
of possible states that the system could
be in there's this particular region
that has these particular properties
that when you're in this area something
interesting happens right so as an
example here again I'm just using the
same thing right plotting the
temperature on the x axis and size on
the y axis well you might say well most
living things that exist exist in this
sub region of that space right most
living things exist somewhere between 0
and 100 roughly degrees Celsius and most
living things are somewhere between uh
how did I put like 10 centimeters and
100 meters if you're looking at like
these very large colonies of cloning
trees and stuff like so this is the kind
of thing that you can say using the
state space formalism and one of the
interesting things is that you can do
with this is described trajectories over
the phase space right so this is sort of
like you know literally drawing a
trajectory over this phase space and
saying okay well the system starts here
and then some perturbation moves the
system towards another state and then
the system has to cycle back so for
example I wake up in the morning I'm a
bit hungry right this is somehow related
in an interesting way to my you know
making coffee and breakfast and then I
eat and then I'm satiated and then I
moved to another area of the phase space
that is me satiated right but you know I
I consume sugar you know as I as I for
example give this talk so sure enough
I'll be hungry later today
so then I'm back where I was and then
this you know so the phase space
description allows us to say something
about the dynamics of a system it allows
us to say something about the way that a
system States evolved over time
so basically the reason I'm talking
about this is that active inference is a
theory of provides and mechanics of or
tells us how living systems are able to
do this right so we we all exist as
living things in a bounded set of states
right we we don't self organize to
dissipation like these things right we
self organize to a very well-defined set
of states the question is how do we how
do we do this an active inference
provides a an answer to that question
active inference tells us about how
things can stay away from basically you
know states that they they want to avoid
and stay in a regime of states that are
compatible with their existence okay
second motivation which you might call
the animals perspective or the Bayesian
room so if you really really really want
to caricature the position that
organisms are in basically organisms are
in what you might call the Bayesian room
chris elias smith has called this the
animals perspective so the the idea of
the bayesian room is that organisms only
ever have access to their sensory input
right and this sensory input isn't
always very reliable the for those of
you who do neurophysiology you'll know
that you know the sensory motor channels
that we deal with are just intrinsically
noisy they have to deal with movement
and variance and there are varying
trustworthiness as well that's kind of
context dependent so you know I spent a
lot of time in London last year and
there's a lot of fog so you learned for
example not to trust your eyes as much
and to listen more than you would for
example in Canada when there's very
little fog so this kind of this kind of
problem that the organism has to solve
is a reverse inference problem in the
sense that it has access only to its
sensory input and it needs to determine
what caused its sensory input so you
know you might hear I've got a a Spock
ear connected to a brain right a very
simple sensory system as as occur in
nature frequently right
so suppose my Spock ear system here's a
snap a crack of some kind right well the
what caused the snap is you know
relevant right sometimes for the
survival of my the Spock ear organism in
this case it may be it was just the wind
moving you know the branches of trees
and a twig snapped maybe it was a tiger
right and the difference is relevant
because the brain we mustn't forget its
main function is to coordinate movement
in a I forget what the the animal is
there there's a there's a very simple
animal that lives in water and it has a
nervous system for the first phase of
its life it moves around and in a
metaphor for tenure what it does when it
reaches maturity is it attaches to a
rock and it digests its nervous system
it's the first thing it does when it
doesn't have to have to generate
movement right when you don't have to
coordinate movement anymore you don't
really need a nervous system so yeah so
out of multiple possibilities for action
the brain has to determine well so what
exactly caused the sensation was that a
tiger or was it just the twig and has to
coordinate action you know the in an
adaptive way as a function of its
inferences so this is another motivation
right active inference is useful because
it tells us how this happens okay that
was the motivation introduction bit we
can now move to predictive processing
unless there are questions about that
opening part are we good all right
okay so predictive processing is a
theory of how the brain works and it's
essentially a an instantiation of active
inference applied to the dynamics of the
brain and it's it's a good starting
point to understand active inference in
part because historically this is how
the sequence kind of originated right
these approaches were developed in
theoretical and computational
neuroscience ha's and only recently
through the work I mean
you know our group at McGill and and the
work of others has been extended to to
model social and cultural phenomena so
we'll start with the brain so you know
neuroscience 101 the traditional view of
cognitive processing that you'll learn
in any neuroscience class is that the
brain is essentially an aggregate of
bottom-up feature detectors so we'll
unpack this sequentially the brain is
first of all the feature detector
meaning that the the more sensory areas
of the brain that are supposed to be
like lower down on the processing
hierarchy what they do is essentially
detect features right so in the primary
visual area for example you're sensitive
to bars and then as you ascend the
cortical hierarchy you and this is the
other key word aggregate right these
statistical features together until you
arrive at something like a complex
percept so two things to note about the
traditional view on the traditional view
the bottom-up signal is the one that's
driving the show right essentially what
the brain is kind of cast as in this on
this view is a kind of passive collector
of sensations right that yet combined
aggregated together and yield you know
the arced world of experience right
another thing to note is that on this
view the the descending connections
right that descend from so-called higher
areas like the prefrontal cortex back
down to the sensory areas these are seen
as modulation or feedback right so the
so on this view the brain is a passive
organ it receives sensations it
aggregates them and the top-down stuff
is just feedback so there are a few
weird things about this for people who
study the brain in more detail one thing
to note for example is that roughly 80%
of the brain's connections are doing
this feedback thing right are descending
so in a sense it would sort of be
surprising that 80% of the brain's
energy budget goes to something that's
just feedback
so I mean another at for someone trained
in philosophy like myself another very
important problem is like where is
meaning supposed to emerge from this
right so somehow I'm supposed to be
aggregating geometric features of
stimuli and then meaning is supposed to
pop out of that somehow it's not clear
how that's supposed to happen as is
often the case in neuroscience we we
give a nice little name to our ignorance
essentially we it's called the binding
problem in cognitive neuroscience so how
is this information bound together to
produce a meaningful stimulus I mean it
you know what we think is that this is
maybe just the wrong way to look at the
problem that maybe no answer is
forthcoming
so the predictive processing viewer the
active inference view flips this on its
head and says ok well maybe maybe this
top-down thing is what the brain is
mainly engaged in maybe that's the main
activity that the brain is busying
itself with so from this point of view
the the main activity of the brain is
essentially to produce these kind of
top-down predictions about what it
should expect to sense next right and
what flows up right so it's
traditionally thought of as the signal
right is is what we call a prediction
error so it's essentially the difference
between what was predicted at a given
moment and what is actually sensed I'll
return to this in a second like in a lot
of detail but a few things to note first
I guess the most important is that
really conceptually it flips the
traditional view of like how the brain
works on its head because what we're
basically saying is well the the
top-down activity is the main driver and
essentially sensory information is
feedback right the the feedback is not
what we thought it was in a sense so
it's it's sort of like moving from a
conception of the brain is a passive
collector of data and a combiner of
you know geometric or statistical
information moving from that to a view
of the brain as a kind of query machine
right it's sort of a perception is like
a Google search right you you you ask a
question and you get an answer this is
so you know a visual cicada is as asking
the world a question essentially so
perception is an answer to that question
so it's a completed version of the
received view in that sense so now we're
gonna get a bit more technical so how
does this work
it works via this broad framework that
we we can call generative modeling
you're gonna see this a lot in the
following slides the scheme is always
basically the same you have two things
to its so when I say the active
inference is simple i I mean it you can
essentially explain it with two circles
on the line as I'll try to do now so the
two circles here represent on the one
hand data right the data that's
available to to us so observations
things that are capable of registering
observations or measurements on the one
hand and on the other the hidden or
latent factors that actually cause the
data that we're observing right so in
this graph causality flows from left to
right right you have states in the world
that cause the blue arrow the data that
we're observing on on the right here and
so what we want to do if we go back to
this problem that I presented of you
know the the brain having to you know
solve this inference problem right is it
a tiger is it a twig so basically the
brain the brain according to active
inference at least what the brain is
busy doing is kind of reversing this
arrow right so the the arrow of
causality goes from hidden States to
data and what we want to do is move from
the data that we have to an inference of
what the most likely causal factors are
that caused the data right so this is I
say data in a kind of broad sense
because it's important to keep in mind
the historical context in which the
methods were initially developed my
mentor at UCL Carl Kristen developed
these generative modeling techniques for
fMRI initially so in fMRI which you have
is a bold signal and which you want to
infer is the underlying neurobiological
activity that caused the bold signal so
just by show of hands how many of you
are familiar with neuroimaging and like
more technically okay so a fair bit of
you just as a refresher for those of you
who don't know when you do fMRI you're
not directly measuring brain activity
right you these fancy heat maps of the
brain that you see are not direct
measurements of brain activity what we
measure is a is a proxy for brain
activity right so it's a it's a
basically a measure of this this bold
signal stands for blood oxygenation
level dependent signal it essentially
consists in putting someone you know in
a brain scanner which is basically a big
magnet and then you measure essentially
a byproduct of oxygen consumption by
neurons in the brain right so what you
what you're measuring is an effect of
the neural activity that you really find
interesting and so what you would like
to do then is from this signal right
from these from this data you want to
infer the most probable neurobiological
activity that caused the data so this is
the technique that was pioneered than
the 90s by Michael Forrest in in the 90s
they were using statistical parametric
mapping which I won't get into very much
but essentially for reasons that I'll
we'll be able to see a bit later these
techniques allow us to move from this
data to a model of of the essentially
the connectivity of the brain that the
most likely connectivity that would have
generated the data that we're interested
in explaining right active inference and
it's more familiar format for those of
you who work on it comes in at a second
level
what happens when the data that we want
to explain is literally the sensory
signals that the brain is receiving all
the time how does that change the
general scheme well it changes it in the
what we're doing now is constructing a
model not just of the underlying
neurobiological activity that caused a
signal that we measured but rather
constructing a model of what's what
causes the sensory signals of an
organism so you know the the the the
major part of what causes our sensory
experience is us acting in the world in
various ways right think I'll think only
of the visual saccades that you're
performing many times a second right you
we are we are as embodied agents are the
main causal driver of our phenomenology
in a sense so active inference per se is
about characterizing this right the it's
about characterizing a model of how our
sensory data were generated so I'll
return to that in a lot of detail later
I just want to quickly say that there's
a new kind of tier of active inference
that that's being developed right now
this is probably the least explored most
cutting-edge application of this this
framework what does it look like when
the data that we're trying to explain is
outcomes of the diagnostic process right
so like the data that I'm trying to
explain for example is a schizophrenia
diagnosis or a depression diagnosis
right so then the model that we're
writing is a model of the process that
generated the diagnostic classification
per se and for me as a philosopher this
is really interesting because this is
where it gets really meta right like
this is where we are part of the model
in a sense we as clinicians and
researchers really are represented in
the model that generates the data if the
data is psychiatric diagnosis anyway the
so the point of generative modeling the
way that it's it's been used for for a
few decades now is this kind of very
simplified pipeline we're on the one
hand you have an experimental
that generates data that you want to
explain and on the other you have a
computational setup that is effectively
a model of the process involved in your
experimental setup so then you get this
kind of circular relation going where
your experimental setup provides data
you can essentially model or create
models of the most probable causal
process to have generated your data that
in turn can be used to refine your
hypotheses and your methodology right
that you're using in your experimental
setup and so there's this kind of
circular motion between modeling work
and computational work that we
capitalize on and essentially in the
generative modeling paradigm okay so
what is a good model a good model is a
model that generates a a small amount of
error so we'll see what that looks like
in the brain the way that so remember I
gave this kind of general framework to
understand what's going on like in the
brain in terms of active inference if we
wanted to unpack it a bit more at any
layer of cortical activity or really of
any neural activity according to this
framework what's what's happening is
that at layers above and at the same
layer any unit is receiving predictions
about what it should sense right and
basically what's going on is a constant
comparison between what the brain
expects to perceive and what it actually
does perceive and the discrepancy
between these two signals is what gets
shuffled up the hierarchy in this kind
of fashion right so I mean interestingly
this happens as early as the retina so I
mean I won't get into the into the
neurobiology too much but the there
there's reason to think that this
predictive architecture stuff happens
everywhere at every level that really
there's no prediction free layer of
cognitive active
yeah as early as the retina like I was
saying so if we want to think about it
metaphorically but we're sort of moving
towards a formalism here like what it
means then to minimize this error
quantity is basically you have a cloud
of data that you're trying to explain
right and you're constructing a model of
how that data was was generated like
what and therefore what you should
expect of that data so in what you're
essentially doing is fitting a curve to
a cloud of data and the prediction error
per se is is this distance here it's
this distance between the value that the
model predicted and the value that
you're actually perceiving so there's a
there's a story to tell about
thermodynamics and information theory
that I'm going to skip over but we can
return to later if you're interested
so essentially according to active
inference / the predictive processing
there are two ways to minimize this this
quantity right this this discrepancy
between what I expected and what I
perceived the first is to change your
model I think it's the most obvious
right if if there's a discrepancy
between what you predicted and what you
perceived the simplest way to reduce the
discrepancy is just to change what you
predicted so we just change the model
we'll see what that means a bit later we
adopt a different model and this model
generates less prediction error than the
original one right which means that it's
better it means that it's more reliably
you know explaining the variance in your
data of course it's always possible to
overfit so I mean this is just a brief
mathematical excursus but for those of
you who have done statistics you'll know
that like if you have n data points you
can always arbitrarily construct a
polynomial function of degree n plus 1
that'll go by all of the points that
you're interested in but capture none of
the trends that you're trying to explain
right so it I just ad hoc you know I
probably can't tell right because it's
so gracefully traced but I ad hoc
constructed a function here which I
assure you
very rigorous one and it passes by all
of the data points as you'll notice but
what you'll also notice is that there is
a trend in the data and that the this
function isn't capturing it anymore so
you might think that if the brain does
something like that in overfits data
then it on the long term it's going to
generate a lot of prediction error and
so you know some disorders you might
think of delusional ideation and this
kind of thing is have been understood in
terms of overfitting so overall you're
better with a slightly simpler model
that generates some error right but that
on average sticks to the the trend and
the data better so this also speaks to a
more general more I guess philosophical
point here is that in this framework the
error is your signal right when we say
like minimizing prediction error we
don't want zero prediction error because
that would mean having zero signal so
one way to think about this is your
model has to be simpler than the reality
that you're modeling right so think of a
map right a model is basically a map a
one-to-one scale map would be completely
useless right like if I had a you know
the a map of this room would be like you
know I wouldn't be able to to look at it
and it wouldn't it wouldn't contain you
know information in a way that could be
used in a useful fashion right the model
has to be simpler than the data this
means that just by construction there
will always be prediction error right
just that's how it works
you need prediction error because it's
your signal okay so first way to
minimize prediction error is to change
your model second way to minimize
prediction error is to change the world
right so if there's this discrepancy
right you know you might want to make
your model more like the world but you
might also just want to make the world
more like your prediction and so
inactive inference / predictive
processing action itself is understood
as a form of self-fulfilling prophecy in
the following sense
you start off with a prediction of
action and you're not moving right so I
don't know like I don't have a prop
handy I usually do but suppose I had a
glass of water handy and I wanted to
reach for it
well the way that it's unpacked in the
predictive processing framework is I
produce a prediction of movement but I'm
not moving right so it's so facto if I'm
not moving and I expect to move that
induces a prediction error right and so
the cool thing about using a prediction
error as your signal is that it updates
over time in real time right so I
basically initiate movements that in
real time reduce this prediction error
so it can be used as a kind of knowledge
driven real-time signal you know that
enables adaptive motor behavior so this
is just what I said
you generate an action prediction you're
not moving therefore a prediction error
is induced and that can be used to guide
online motor behavior okay so now I'd
ask you to buckle in really tightly
because we're gonna do some math so
we're gonna look at the generative
models themselves I've talked a lot
about the models etc so what are these
models so remember the general flavor of
this is we have data and we're trying to
infer the the most probable latent
States that cause the data that we're
trying to explain right so causality
flows in this direction inference flows
in that direction okay so how exactly do
you quantify you know how well a model
explains your data so the way that you
typically will do this is by
constructing several alternative models
right the that are each each encode a
different hypothesis about how the data
might have been caused and then you
evaluate how well that model accounts
for the variance in your data so if you
want to compress that algorithm into
like a quantity what you get is this
spooky variational free-energy thing
which you know you might also just call
the model evidence or abound on the
model evidence basically this
variational free-energy thing is a
measure of how much evidence is provided
by the data for a given model of the
process right so it's important to
stress this the free-energy isn't an
energy in the sense of thermodynamics
right it's a it's a measure of how well
your model explains the variance in your
data so that I think that's an important
takeaway you know to like understand
what is going on here right it the let
me repeat the variational free energy is
just basically a measure of how well
your model explains the data the
variance in your data yes yeah okay well
so the the model evidence itself if you
actually try to compute it usually just
for calculation reasons you won't be
able to do it typically it's because
these always involve a normalization
term you kind of have to divide by this
term and this term calculating it
involves summing over an infinite set of
states so basically you can't do it
analytically and so what you do instead
is you construct this quantity of the
variational free energy which which is
basically an upper bound on the model
evidence what that means is that like
the model evidence the your variational
free energy basically tells you you at
least have this much evidence right you
might have a bit more but you at least
have that much evidence from your model
for your model right so so just to
rehearse this again right so always the
same formula you have some data you're
trying to construct the most probable
model of the process that caused the
data and you get added through inference
so and so this is what the models
typically look like and Florence once
told me that just presenting these
models is basically an act of
intimidation
this one is very consoling and
comforting thank you so so rather than
the engage in this act of violence all
I'll try to unpack a bit what what these
models are right so the most basic
generative model is this thing here and
this thing here is just this thing here
right everyone sees right you have your
data you have your most probable causal
states and a relation of inference
between them all right so here you have
it's just flipped here you have your
data right the most probable causal
state that caused your data that you're
trying to infer and now what we're doing
is just adding a bit of mathematical
niceties mainly we're parameterizing
these relations right so this a thing is
just a likelihood mapping and basically
what it does is specify for every state
if this state was actually the case
right what kind of data would I expect
to see right so for example if it is
night I would expect it to be dark
outside this is the kind of thing that
this a characterizes so one important
distinction to make sense of these
graphs is that the circles are either
your data or the quantities that you're
trying to infer right and the squares
are essentially parameters of the
relations between these circles right so
that they characterize the arrows
between so like I was saying S is just
your state that you're trying to infer
oh is your data a is your likelihood
mapping from your state's to your
observations basically like I said
assuming that this state is the case
what what is the probability of
observing this or that and D is just
your prior beliefs over States so like
independently of any observations that
you might make what what do you think
the state is right so just I'll run
through some of the math right so if you
see on the left hand side here s equals
D is just saying well my guess about the
state independent of any data is just my
prior about the state right pretty
simple this o equals a s thing again
it's just describing this relation that
the likelihood mapping has right your
your outcome just is a combination of
this mapping between your states and
observations and the your beliefs about
states and here to the right what you
see in a mathematical form that I won't
get into too much is that your the state
that you predict right your posterior
estimate over States is equal to some
combination that I won't get into too
much of your prior beliefs and what you
learn from your observations from the
data and how that relates to states
right so these look very intimidating at
first but like we can unpack them in the
way that's okay so these were the models
up into that we were using up until 2015
roughly and in 2014 15 16 what happened
was that we started considering temporal
depth and temporality so here we're
adding and it looks a bit more
complicated but we're really just
stacking the first layer model right
does everyone see that like see this
thing here is just this right so
basically the only thing that we've
added here is this B matrix and the B
matrix specifies your beliefs about the
way that states transition over time
again independently of the observations
that you're making this is very clear
from the equations here to the left so
it just says your state at time T plus 1
is a combination of this B matrix right
that captures your beliefs about the way
states transition and the state at time
T all right not nothing exorbitant or a
complicated and again the posterior
thing is just telling you okay your your
posterior belief about a state is just
equal to some combination of your state
and B in the past your state and B in
the future and what you're seeing
in the present right so again it looks
intimidating but it's actually less
complicated than it is I I know it has
been all 2020 this is this presentation
of the material is was developed by one
of my close collaborators and friend
friends Kasper Hesse at the University
of Amsterdam this is from a paper that
we've pre printed now called deeply-felt
effect which I mean besides articulating
emotional inference using the active
inference framework also presents a
tutorial of the more formal kind of
package that underwrites active
inference so if you're interested I can
send you the paper okay so so so far
we've talked about perception at from
time from moment to moment right this
this relation between o and s mediated
by a then if you consider it you know
the the sequence of states what you're
doing is introducing beliefs about the
way the world transitions States evolve
over time independently of your
observations you'll notice that your
prior here has effectively disappeared
from these steps here because your prior
just feeds in your first kind of
estimation and then it kind of goes on
so you're really just using s2 as your
new prior for the next time sorry s1 is
your prior for the the next time step
and so on okay but so far this this
could have just been a tutorial on
reinforcement learning active inference
does something special which is this so
again don't panic this is just what
we've just seen all I did here was add a
circle or which is this policy selection
thing this pie thing here so inactive
inference the way that action selection
is implemented is essentially by
choosing transition matrices by choosing
your beliefs about the way that the
world changes over time so again we have
these B matrices that we just discussed
here right
these beliefs about the way the states
in the world transition well what this
policy thing this policy selector does
up here is effectively choose a series
of B matrices right so to act is to have
beliefs about the way you think the
world should evolve in in this kind of
self confirming way that we discussed
earlier and all the stuff that the top
does is just like put the variational
free-energy thing into into the loop so
this is definitely beyond the level of
mathematical discussion that I had in
mind for today but essentially you have
this G thing G is just your expected
free energy right so it's it's the
amount of free energy that you expect
for every possible action that you could
take and essentially what this thing is
doing is selecting the action that leads
to the lowest free energy right so again
it's just this action selection thing
that leads to you know prediction error
minimization or that runs on prediction
error minimization which you'll notice
is that PI again is a circle it's one of
these quantities that we have to infer
so contrary to you know more traditional
schemes in motor control where you just
program a command and it's affected
inactive inference your little agent is
effectively trying to infer well what am
i doing right no but really like oh well
on the basis of your prior beliefs right
and on the data that you're receiving
from your sense is what is it that I
must be doing right so I'm this again
contains a lot of weird math that I'm
not going to go into but I just wanted
to show you this because it's cool so
here you have your generative process
here you have your generative process so
this is just a basically a model of like
a model in the sense of we are modeling
just the process that actually generates
the data that's sort of like invisible
invisible to us right so this is sort of
like it's hidden
to us but like there is a process that
generates our data and this is a poor
knee style factor graph representation
of the generative model that I just
showed you it's it's all the same terms
right you've got your bees your DS and
your eyes and all that I won't get into
how you go from one from one to the
other because it's a little complicated
I was just putting this slide up because
I wanted you to notice two things well
it's the same thing but it's it has two
elements where the process that
generates our data and the model of our
data like where they meet is it two
points you have these you things up here
which are the actual actions that you're
performing right and this these the O's
your your observations so basically the
model the generative model and the
generative process meet at action and
observation like that's that's sort of
the two connective points I mean this is
complicated and we can return to it then
this is the last technical thing I
wanted to show you like where we're at
now with the modeling is that we we
introduce a new layer of States into the
model that are about States at the lower
layer so in our new worker working on
metacognition emotional content and kind
of self-control mindfulness meditation
and this stuff so what we did here is
connect a layer of states at the top
here with their own transition matrices
and everything two states at the lower
level so what we've begun doing is
treating States oops is treating states
at the lower level here as observations
so like we're treating the results of
inference as new data right that the
system can can then use to make
inferences about itself and basically
how well it's doing so I told you this
paper is called deeply-felt effect
because we use this kind of layered
structure to account for basically
beliefs about oneself right and
eventually self-control in this kind of
thing
for the sake of people who may get a
little lost when the discussion is too
abstract
anymore if you could think of a couple
concrete examples without technical
language going beyond something like oh
here's how a monkey something more like
how did you help make sense of human
emotions and moods for example how sure
checking in with oneself okay well so
this bottom part of the model you can
make it do you can make it do whatever
you're interested in making it do right
so you could have a model of I don't
know a con for having a conversation
right so in this kind of model of having
it might be simpler to explain that bit
just with this so you know the data that
you have to explain might be you know
configurations spatial configurations a
you know of expression in someone's face
you know the the auditory sensations
that you're registering right so for
each of these modalities you have an a
matrix that specifies the way that the
you believe these sensations are
typically related to the states that
cause them right and you have this
policy selection thing that affects
beliefs about the way that states
evolves right so in a conversation for
example right you would be resolving
that continuously I would be inferring
these lower-level states like what is
Sam telling me now right and I would be
selecting a policy that you know that
facilitates this interaction that
ideally gets us like to some kind of
coupled point where were able to
interact so the the point of adding
these additional layers is that now I
can make inferences about my inferences
I can be like well am I sure that Sam
feels good today you know like he I
don't know like he he seems tired or
something or I don't know like yeah it's
it's things to do with for example
confidence in your own judgments how
well am i doing you know how how do I
feel about these inferences that I'm
making this kind of thing so inferences
about our inferences and you
the reason why this is important I think
just generally for for humans is that'll
you know I'm telling this to you you
know in particular most of human
thinking is thinking through other minds
right it's thinking about right other
minds the way you're describing it now
it seems like there may be two things
conflated or maybe just one part of them
being I'm talking to you and I'm
thinking I'm thinking something about
the nature of our conversation and
that's a kind of self-consciousness if
I'm thinking right I wonder if I'm
making a good impression
right so what what it brings to mind is
is there a generic self-consciousness
like you just have lots of those
thoughts because this version is just
very specific I just have one question
right have one hypothesis but in real
life these things come in bundles it
ends with a whole and and that's what we
would then call an effective stance
let's see yeah absolutely I mean uneasy
with you
so I'm engaging with the lots of
alternative so so how would you model
that in other words it's not simply one
thing one bit of metacognition or rate
of reflection on the nature of
interaction it's a different I would
describe it informally again it's like a
different stance or a different one
important thing is that we can entertain
more than one different model right so
there's some interesting work by ezel
Mora I think who essentially implements
like a simple and these are very simple
toy systems for now what we're doing now
is scaling them up to human systems but
it's basically a bird simulation and
it's it's it listens to eight different
birds
and it recognizes them essentially
because it entertains eight different
models that might correspond to this or
that so the capacity to simultaneously
entertain different models might help
different if I say okay I'm uncertain
where I stand with Brett and so I have
to entertain many different models
versus I'm just having one policy okay
so you're right well the thing to note
about is that the thing to note about
this is that this top level of inference
makes this bottom level accessible to
the system right so basically inferences
at at this bottom level just happen
right so they they guide action but in
an implicit sense whereas these states
are literally about the states below so
attentional States for example exist at
this level right States about my sensory
states that helps right which then has
destructive effect let's say on my
attention of state versus having one
that is coherently great sort of
reinforcing the particular anyway I
guess know that you what you're seeing
is is that that's that's really like I
think an important point I mean and in
in work that we have in that I'm not
going to be presenting today which is
basically like where we're at right now
we've got a three layer system going to
explain mindfulness meditation this is a
work by Lars Lars Sam Ted Smith in
particular that we're doing with Karl
for student at UCL we're basically on
top of this we have an addition yet an
additional layer
make the attentional states opaque to
the system this is already there kind of
implicitly right look we have a B matrix
that that links these different things
so we already have beliefs about the way
that these higher-order mental states
are transitioning what would it look
like if we implemented policy selection
there because you can it's a B matrix so
why not just like hook these up to a
higher level pie
you could you could and that's what we
end up doing in the anyway so I guess
I'll be putting this on YouTube policy
is a sequence of B matrices okay right
because that's what it is
to select an action under this framework
is to change your beliefs about the way
that states are supposed to evolve right
yeah it's a well it's it in the Morse
well because in in the most simple case
it's just a series of B matrices but
what if you're considering
counterfactual depth right like yeah
then you have like trees of B matrices
and so forth can create a network yeah
there's feedback between different
contexts
well let me try to just finish I have
about like ten minutes left of material
pointed you'll come back to because for
me the so it's appealing again that you
get these harder to the levels and it
seems like you're getting more however
the more layers you add it seems to me
you don't say have more data do you so
exactly a problem of like your
complexities back to the overfitting
whatever having way more complexity
modeling actually I mean that's a really
good question and we struggled really
hard you know last time I was in London
a lot of what we did was ask well do we
really need a third level it can't we
just do policy selection at the second
level but the key thing is this opacity
thing is that to make these states of
inference accessible to the system to to
allow the system to use them as data for
further information
I mean we've sort of seen it before but
basically Bayes Bayes rule is just a way
to combine prior probabilities with your
likelihoods to get posterior probability
so yeah Bayes is important so I put it
on a little crap so your prior
probability is just the probability of
some event before any evidence is taken
into account your likelihood is the
likelihood of some event the probability
of some event given some evidence that
should be probability of some of that
given some evidence so just to
illustrate the difference if Houdini
magics away an elephant on stage well
you know there's a high likelihood that
the elephant is gone you can even go on
stage and collect more data the elephant
clearly is gone
right but we know that there's a low
prior probability that elephants just D
materialized because elephants are solid
objects and right those don't typically
D materialized so Bayes rule is just a
way to combine these quantities
optimally so basically the cool thing
about this is that you can always use
your posterior at one
step so the result of combining your
prior and your likelihood as your new
prior at the next step so there's this
nice kind of bootstrapping thing that
you can do and the way that this relates
to what we've been talking about is
basically the descending connections
right they carry your priors and your
prediction error is basically always
integrating the data that you're that
you're generating so it's it's
essentially a likelihood and the
Bayesian brain says okay well this is
what the brain essentially looks like
right you've got likelihoods flowing up
in the form of unexplained prediction
error and prior probabilities flowing
down right in the form of neural
prediction these these schemes are
typically hierarchical I hinted at this
earlier the reason why they are is that
as you mystically as you go up the
hierarchy the things that are
represented are more stable over time
and as you go towards the more sensory
and things change faster right so for
those of you who are familiar with
Fourier analysis basically you can take
any image and decompose it into
frequency bands right so high spatial
frequency and low spatial frequency
information right which which you'll
notice so high spatial frequencies to
the right here low spatial frequencies
to the left here and what you'll notice
is that in a conversation hi-spec high
spatial frequency information changes
much faster than low spatial frequency
information I mean unless you're someone
like myself you know moves around the
face and like makes funny expressions
like typically most people like you know
that their lips move faster than the
rest of their face right so you might
think that this is implemented in the
hierarchies that the brain encodes
the the hierarchies of information that
the brain encodes and according to the
predictive processing framework this is
precisely what we see so I'll skip over
that all right so yeah so you have
hierarchies of information that encode
regularities that are time sensitive and
you have prediction error minimization
going across the this hierarchy and it
essentially explains
the way that the brain reacts to stimuli
alright so that was predictive
processing we can scale this up is what
I submit to you now so I have this
winter is coming just to talk about my
favorite example of active inference
it's like well when I get cold I don't
know about you but I put on a parka
especially like in Canada it's cold
right so that we can cast this as active
inference as well I think so the the
point for the next two slides is
basically going to be it's not just the
brain that engages in active inference
it's every cell in your body every organ
system in your body and effectively
maybe social groups as well and this is
what we you know we work on ok the last
bit of math that I want to introduce to
you I think is simpler than the rest
it's called a Markov blanket and what I
want to submit to you is the rock cells
organs animals social groups basically
anything that exists at all has a Markov
blanket so a Markov blanket is just a
way to use statistics to answer what is
traditionally a philosophical question
right the philosophical question being
what does it mean to exist what does it
mean to exist as a thing right what does
it mean to be a thing so I mean if you
ask a philosopher they'll tell you like
a story about metaphysics and you know
like type token and identity theory and
whatever we've issued all of this for
something much more simple which is to
say okay well if we're interested in a
system right so suppose the system that
we're interested in is the brain right
because we've talked about it and we
want to differentiate it from the
environment and which Siachen in which
it is embedded what we'll do essentially
is introduce or define a third set of
states that mediates the causal
relations between the system that were
interested in defining and its
environment so these are known as
sensory and active States so these are
metaphors of course the the way that
they're defined is by their connectivity
right so sensory states cause internal
States
but are not caused by internal states
and active states caused that are not
caused by external states so I mean the
point of doing this is to say okay to
exist is to be endowed with some degree
of conditional independence relative to
your environment right so if you
consider this massive gas right here
it's not a system because it'll just
dissipate right like there's no robust
sense in which it's independent of its
environment in any sense like you know
it's gone right so a Markov blanket is a
way of saying conditioned on the
existence of this set of states the
sensory in the active States the
internal states of the system are
independent of the external states of
the world is that clear to everyone okay
so active inference then is a story
about how internal states that which
encode our model right and the active
States which are like our skeletal
muscles and so forth change to minimize
free energy and the end effect is to
allow this inference process to happen
right so the the inference here meaning
that the free energy or prediction error
diminishes right so making the internal
states more like the external States and
vice versa again this is just this story
right it's just that as we've seen
inference also occurs through action so
basically like you have the state
estimation bit going on here where we're
kind of inferring what should be going
on in the world you have the policy
selection bit here but this is just the
story that we told right but just now
presented in terms of like the existence
of the system I'm gonna skip through
that so so yeah this is a drawing by the
famous physicist Huygens and yellow
Brandenburg has it in one of papers on
this like an important point is that
like an advantage of using active
inference over other frameworks is that
it just it comes from physics right so
you solve this inference problem but
using using a framework that basically
says well inference is sort of like a
rock falling down a cliff you're just
falling to an an energy minimum right so
the the reason it's called variational
free energy is with an app is analogous
is with analogy to the thermodynamic
quantity free energy right in
thermodynamics free energy is the amount
of energy left in a system that can
perform work right in the information
theoretic context the variational free
energy is basically the amount of wiggle
room you still have on your parameters
to get a better representational grip of
the situation right it's like yeah how
much room is left on your parameters to
do work to do representational work okay
last thing basically that I'll be
talking about today so here's our Markov
blanketed system again I submit to you
that all of the components of this
system are also systems right this is
the observation that we started with I'm
a system I'm an organism but I'm made of
networks of organs that are themselves
systems and the organs themselves are
systems of cells and so forth so every
component of a Markov blanket is itself
Markov blanketed so in this 2015 paper
by Carl Kristen which i think is the
first and literature to do this they
effectively connected two levels of
description so what they showed is that
on the assumption that what you see here
first is I think seven eight cells eight
cells that share a generative model and
over time reach a target configuration
so it's basically a little creature with
a head and a tail everyone sees that and
so what you have plotted here is
basically the beliefs of each cell about
what kind of cell they are essentially
and so you have your free energy plotted
here and so what you see is all of these
cells share the same generative model so
basically they're able to infer their
place relative to other cells so long as
they're able to commute
with other cells because we all have the
same expectations right we all expect to
sense the same kinds of things so
basically the the little units start off
and there's free energy spikes because
they're trying to figure out what's
going on but then as they communicate
the the free energy starts to go down
until it reaches a minimum value and
when it's reached its minimum value here
the simulation reaches its target
configuration right so that for me this
was like an eye-opening moment where I
kind of you know with Carl realized that
you know this is how you effectively
connect levels of organization right
units at one level sharing a generative
model are able to enact a target
morphology so from there we generalized
this is from our one of our physics of
life reviews papers we're essentially
just telling the story of how at any
Markov blanketed system itself is
composed of Markov blanketed systems so
you have this kind of recursively nested
systems of systems of systems of systems
approach which you might think of as a a
vertical stack of systems I say vertical
because there are two dimensions to this
system really there's a vertical stack
where like cells compose organs which
compose organ networks and so on and so
on but there's also a horizontal stack
where at any scale of interest like the
the relevant actors like cells for
example are also in the process of niche
construction they're they're
constructing an environment for
themselves and they're effectively
sharing a physical environment yeah
so this kind of gets us here right where
we started at least I hope I've made the
point that you know via active inference
there's at least the possibility for
something like an integrated science of
culture mind and brain that takes all of
these levels seriously right and I'm
just going to skip through this right to
the thank you slides yeah so that's what
I wanted to share today thank you for
your attention
thank you to my hungers special thanks
to the people listed particularly those
of you who came and yes thanks for your
attention
[Music]